A Guide to the Flowerdew Hundred Papers, 1673-1893
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Flowerdew Hundred Papers, 1673-1893
Library of Virginia
28758
.35 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
For deeds, land grants, plats, and surveys, use negative photostats.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Emily Dunn, 508 Seneca Road, Richmond, Virginia, 27 March 1975
Alternative Form Available
Negative photostats of deeds, land grants, plats, and surveys.
Historical Information
Flowerdew Hundred was patented and named by Sir George Yeardley in 1618. In 1624, the property was transferred to Abraham Peirsey whose daughter, Mrs. Elizabeth Stephens, repatented it in 1636. She sold it to William Barker and the property eventually came into the possession of John Taylor who willed it to his heirs in 1707 (proved 1709). His heiresses who married John and Francis Hardyman and [Henry?] Duke sold the property to [Joshua] Poythress. The lands were eventually reassembled by purchase and descent from the several owners and became the property of the Willcox family.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1673-1893, relating to Flowerdew Hundred Plantation in Prince George County, Virginia, containing abstracts, accounts, birth records, deeds, diaries, estate records, genealogies, judicial records, land grants, land surveys, letters, memorandums, plats, receipts, summonses, tax records, and wills. Papers concern the ownership of Flowerdew Hundred by the Poythress and Willcox families. Deeds, plats, and surveys are mostly for and of Flowerdew Hundred. Also of interest are John Poythress Wilcox's (1805-1857) diary, 1827, of his trip to the northeastern United States and Canada; birth records, 1752-1788, of slaves recorded on a land patent, 28 September 1730, to Thomas Roberts of Prince George County; copy of a deed, 1624, from Sir George Yeardley (1588-1627) to Abraham Peirsey for Flowerdew Hundred.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Division of Flowerdew Hundred, 24 April 1673, between Robert and Sarah Lucy and Phillip and Elzabeth Limbry., 4 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder a)
- Land grant, 22 November 1682, for 550 acres in Charles City County, Virginia, to John Evans of Charles City County, signed by Lieutenant Governor Sir Henry Chicheley., 1 leaf, incomplete, negative photostat. (Folder b)
- Plat, 10 October 1709, of Flowerdew Hundred Plantation, Prince George County, Virginia., 3 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder c)
- Deed of lease, 9 July 1725, for 300 acres in Prince George County from John and Henrietta Maria Hardyman to Joseph [Joshua] Poythress. Deed recorded in Prince George County Court 13 July 1725., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder d)
- Deed of release, 10 July 1725, from John and Henrietta Maria Hardyman to Joseph [Joshua] Poythress. Recorded in Prince George County Court 13 July 1725., . (Folder e)
- Land grant, 28 September 1730, for 400 acres in Prince George County to Thomas Roberts, signed by Lieutenant Governor Sir William Gooch. Includes a list, 1752-1788, of births of slaves, probably in Prince George County., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder f)
- Land grant, 10 January 1735, for 400 acres in Amelia County, Virginia, to Henry Walthall, signed by Sir William Gooch., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder g)
- Plat and survey, 31 October 1764, for Joshua Poythress., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder h)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1798-1893, relating to the Willcox family. (Folder i)
  - Tax receipt, 1832, for taxes paid by John V. Wil[l]cox, Prince George County., 1 leaf.
  - Receipt, 27 August 1832, from Dan Lyon to David May., 2 pages.
  - Letter, 22 May 1798, from John V. Willcox, Petersburg, Virginia, to his father discussing business and family matters., 1 leaf.
  - Account, November 1835, for Richard Eppes from the United States Circuit Court, North Carolina District, for appearing as a witness in John V. Willcox and Thomas Willcox vs. Kemp Plummer., 1 leaf.
  - Letter, 25 March 1837, from William Oxley, Liverpool, England, to John P. Wil[l]cox, Petersburg, sending plum cake for the christening banquet of one of Willcox's children., 1 leaf.
  - Deed, 9 November 1826, for land adjoining Flowerdew Hundred in Prince George County from William Selden and Thomas Cocke, executors of Miles Selden, to John V. Willcox., 4 pages.
  - Decree, May 1869, issued in Mary Jane Willcox vs. D. W. Sherman, Sheriff of Prince George County, admr of John V. Willcox, deceased, et. al., 4 pages.
  - Deed, 1 June 1869, from Charles S. Stringfellow, special commissioner, to Mary Jane Willcox for land deeded to her by John V. Willcox 6 December 1858, but for which the deed was lost during the Civil War. Recorded in Petersburg Hustings Court 3 June 1869., 4 pages.
  - Notice, 23 September 1871, concerning Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf.
  - Deed, 28 September 1871, for 173 29/100 acres in Prince George County from Mary J. Willcox in her own right and as executor of John P. Willcox, and others to Susan P. P. Willcox. Recorded in Prince George County Court 11 November 1871., 3 pages.
  - Deed, 28 September 1871, for 218.10 acres in Prince George County from Mary J. Willcox in her own right and as executor of John P. Willcox, and others to William M. Willcox. Recorded in Prince George County Court House 27 November 1871., 3 pages.
  - Deed, 28 September 1871, for 50 acres in Prince George County from William M Willcox and Susan Willcox his wife and others to Mary J. Willcox. Recorded in Prince George County Court 11 November 1871., 3 pages.
  - Deed, 27 April 1872, for 238 35/100 acres in Prince George County from John G. Dunn and Eliza P. Dunn, his wife, to Mary J. Willcox. Recorded in Prince George County Court 29 April 1872., 3 leaves.
  - Deed, 19 January 1884, for 1/4th interest in 218.10 acres in Prince George County from John G. Dunn and Eliza P. Dunn, his wife, to Susan P. P. Willcox. Recorded in Prince George County Court 20 February 1884., 3 pages.
  - Deed, 19 January 1884, for 1/4th interest in 218.10 acres in Prince George County from R. Bolling Willcox and Martha L. Willcox, his wife, to Mary J. Willcox. Recorded in Prince George County Court 20 February 1884., 5 pages.
  - Account, 14 October 1893, of the estate of Mary J. Willcox with Susan P. P. Willcox, her executrix., 4 pages.
- Plat and survey, 25 March 1806, of Flowerdew Hundred for John V. Willcox., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder j)
- Plat and survey, 25 March 1806, of Flowerdew Hundred for John V. Willcox., 3 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder k)
- Plat and survey, 31 March 1808, of Flowerdew Hundred for John V. Willcox., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder l)
- Plat and survey, 1 December 1812, of 1002 acres in Prince George County adjoining Flowerdew Hundred, made for Mary M. Peachy., 3 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder m)
- Plat and survey, 11 December 1812, of 1002 acres adjoining Flowerdew Hundred, made for Mary M. Peachy., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder n)
- Plat and survey, 15 September 1818, of 1130 acres in Prince George County adjoining Flowerdew Hundred, made for the estate of William Eppes, deceased., 1 leaf, negative photostat. (Folder o)
- Deed, 1822, from William A. and Martha Harrison to John V. Willcox., 2 leaves, incomplete, negative photostats. (Folder p)
- Journal, July-September 1827, of John Poythress Willcox detailing his journey through the northeastern United States and Canada. Typescript copy of journal is accession 31026b., 29 leaves, negative photostats; 24 leaves, typescript. (Folder q)
- Deed, 1 October 1828, for a town lot in Petersburg, Virginia, from John V. Willcox to John P. Willcox. Recorded in Petersburg Hustings Court 3 November 1828., 2 leaves. (Folder r)
- Letter, 20 March 1832, from Alexander Beegleston to John V. Willcox concerning a summons for Beegleston to appear in court as a witness., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder s)
- Deed, n.y. [1624], from Sir George Yeardley to Abraham Piersey., 1 leaf, fragment, photostat. (Folder t)
- Memorandum, n.d., concerning lands purchased from Frederick Jones by J. Poythress., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder u)
- Memorandum, n.d., concerning 50 acres allotted to H. Hart and his wife in the division of George Hatch's estate., 1 leaf, negative photostat. (Folder v)
- Plat and survey, n.d., of 200 acres adjacent to Joshua Poythress's land., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder w)
- Accounts, n.d., of Joshua Poythress., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder x)
- Survey, n.d., of 565 acres called Hawk's Hill., 2 leaves, negative photostats. (Folder y)
- Miscellaneoud notes relating to Flowerdew Hundred. (Folder z)
  - abstract of deed dated 1624, for Flowerdew Hundred, from Sir George Yeardley to Abraham Piersey. Also includes notes on Yeardley, Piersey, and Flowerdew Hundred., 4 leaves, 3 handwritten, 1 typed.
  - Judicial record, 16 November 1627, at James City, Virginia. Lady Temperance Yeardley confirmed conveyance of Flowerdew Hundred from her husband Sir George Yeardley to Abraham Percy [Piersey]., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - abstract of records, 1627, concerning Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Land grant, 15 October 1636, for 1000 acres in Charles City County, known as Flowerdew Hundred, to Elizabeth Steven., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract, 1673, concerning the division of land owned by John Barker between his daughters Sarah Lucy and Elizabeth Limbry., 1 leaf.
  - Patent, 24 April 1673, of Flowerdew Hundred, dividing it between Robert and Sarah Lucy and Phillip and Elzabeth Limbry., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract of land grant, 22 November 1682, of 557 acres to John Evans., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract of land grant, 10 October 16[82?], for 818 acres in Charles City County, Virginia, to John Evans, adjoining 557 acres previously granted., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract concerning rent, 21 April 1690, for land granted to John Evans., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract of will, 5 April 1707, of John Taylor of Prince George County., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Copy of plat, 10 October 1709, of Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract of deed, 9 July 1725, for 150 acres in Prince George County from John Hardyman and Henrietta Maria Hardyman to Joseph [Joshua] Poythress., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract of deed, 9 July 1725, for 150 acres in Prince George County from John Hardyman and Henrietta Maria Hardyman to Joseph [Joshua] Poythress., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract of deed of release, 10 July 1725, from John Hardyman and Henrietta Maria Hardyman to Joseph [Joshua] Poythress., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Copy of deed, 9 October 1732, for 250 acres (Flowerdew Hundred) in Prince George County, from Elizabeth Duke to Joshua Poythress., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Abstract of will, 17 January 1739/40, of Joshua Poythress of Prince George County., 2 leaves, transcripts.
  - Abstract of plat and survey, 31 October 1764, of Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Copy of will, 9 February 1782, of Mary Poythress, recorded 1788., 2 leaves, transcripts.
  - Copy of deed, 2 October 1790, for part of Flowerdew Hundred from William and Mary Poythress to William Samuel Peachy of Amelia County., 2 leaves, handwriteen, 1 leaf, typescript.
  - Transcript of will, 27 June 1796, of Edward Willcox of Dinwiddie County, Virginia, recorded in the Petersburg Hustings Court 3 December 1798., 1 leaf, typescript.
  - Transcript of deed of manumission, 14 October 1799, from Littleberry Wil[l]cox of Halifax County, North Carolina, to Gabriel Cox. Recorded in Petersburg Hustings Court 2 September 1800., 1 leaf, typescript.
  - Copy of plat, 1 December 1812, of 1002 acres in Prince George County adjoining Flowerdew Hundred, made for Mary M. Peachy., 1 leaf, transcript.
  - Copy of deed, 5 June 1814, for parcel of land in Petersburg from John V. Willcox and Susanna Willcox to James Butler, a free man of color. Recorded in Petersburg Hustings Court, 6 June 1814., 4 pages, transcripts.
  - Receipt, 22 September 1881, from the Virginia Historical Society to William M. Willcox for loan of papers relating to Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf.
  - Notes, n.d., listing papers relating to Flowerdew Hundred., 2 pages.
  - Abstracts, n.d., of legislative acts relating to Flowerdew Hundred., 2 leaves.
  - Notes, n.d., on papers relating to Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf.
  - Notes, n.d., concerning land grants, deeds, and plats for lands of the Poythress family., 4 leaves.
  - Plat and miscellaneous notes, n.d., of Flowerdew Hundred., 2 pages.
  - Transcript of letters, n.d., mentioning Flowerdew Hundred. Includes map of plantations along southside of the James River and Appomattox River., 2 pages.
  - List, n.d., of the spellings for Flowerdew Hundred from 1623 to 1709., 1 leaf.
  - List, n.d., of owners of Flowerdew Hundred from ca. 16[17] to 1800s., 1 leaf.
  - List, n.d., of places in Hening's Statutes which mention Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf.
  - Notes, n.d., relating to Flowerdew Hundred and surrounding lands., 2 pages.
  - Notes, n.d., concerning ownership of Flowerdew Hundred in the 1600s. Two addresses on reverse side., 2 pages.
  - Notes, n.d., concerning the succession of ownership of Flowerdew Hundred from John Taylor to Joshua Poythress., 1 leaf.
  - Notes, n.d., concerning Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf.
  - Notes, n.d., concerning Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf.
  - Notes, n.d., concerning Flowerdew Hundred., 1 leaf.
  - Biographical notes, n.d., about Sir George Yeardley., 1 leaf.
  - Genealogical notes, n.d., concerning Sir George Yeardley and his family., 1 leaf.